welcome back to my YouTube channel
everybody my guest today is Mr John
kiraku a former CIA officer he was the
chief of counterterrorist operations in
Pakistan after 911 and today with John
we'll talk about many different things
first the Saudi connection to 911 the
interrogation of Abu zubida and his
personal story which is pretty peculiar
thanks for your time John thanks for
joining me today my pleasure thanks for
the invitation would you like to tell us
something about yourself like what's
your background what happened how you
ended up being having such an important
role in Pakistan after 911 just to give
my viewers some context of uh what we're
gonna discuss today sure I joined the
CIA uh coming out of graduate school I
started in January of 1990 I spent the
first half of my career as an analyst
working on the Middle East served
overseas in that position uh learned to
speak uh Arabic fluently and then um
after seven years I I got bored in
analysis and I made an unusual change to
counterterrorism operations I served in
in Athens for a couple of years and then
back at headquarters training Middle
Eastern intelligence services and
counterterrorism operations uh 911 took
place and uh on the strength of my my
operational experience in Athens and
elsewhere uh around the Middle East and
my Arabic language skills they sent me
to Pakistan as the chief of
counterterrorism operations I left the
CIA in 200 uh the middle of
2004 I went into the private sector for
a little while and then I blew the
whistle on the cia's torture program
which I believed to be illegal immoral
unethical I know that we'll get into
that then I went to the uh Senate
Foreign Relations Committee under John
Kerry as uh as the senior
investigator had a little bit of a break
after that which again we'll get into
and um for the last 10 years I've been a
radio host a journalist an
author that kind of thing well yes I
think that the overview that you gave us
is complete and we'll touch all the
points that you mentioned so I think
that the most important thing that we
will be discussing today kick off from
the kidnapping of Abu zua who back then
was if I remember well the third leader
in charge of al-Qaeda and uh being the
counterterrorism chief of operations
back then you led a whole operations how
did you guys track him down it was hard
uh you know we learned after the fact
that we had been close for a long time
sometimes we were three days behind
sometimes we were an hour behind we we
broke into Apartments where there was
still warm food on the table where we
had just missed him so we used a a large
team of people to track him down and we
just couldn't we just couldn't find him
we used we used human intelligence we
used electronic intelligence and we just
simply couldn't find him and so in the
end I asked that CIA headquarters send a
targeting analyst to Pakistan a friend
of mine
um to uh to help us narrow the possible
locations and he came out and uh he
started doing what targeting analysts do
that is going through sometimes millions
of pieces of data just mostly metadata
uh trying to to locate someone he he he
took a large piece of Butcher Block
paper uh and wrote Abu Zeda in the
center put a circle around it and then
around that he wrote all of the people
the phone numbers and the email
addresses of everybody who had been in
touch with abuaba and then around that
on a third level he wrote the same
information for the people who had been
in touch with Abu Zeda and so finally he
came to me after after analyzing this
information for two weeks he came to me
and he said look I just can't get it
down to any fewer than 14 possible sites
well we had never we had never rated
more than two sites in a single night
and so I cabled headquarters I said we
need a big team we need guns ammunition
night vision goggles secure
Communications uh bulletproof vests
battering rams cash you need it or you
you name it rather and uh and we we
received it and so on the night of the
raid we hit 13 of 14 sites one was
deemed to be a mistake it was a pay
phone and um what finally got us
abua was he had made
one critical mistake and that was that
he accessed his email account with a
landline and that allowed us
to specifically pinpoint his location uh
and I want to add something about ABA uh
we believed at the time that he was the
number three in al-Qaeda and so he was
the first high value Target that we were
able to
locate um he was not the number three in
al-Qaeda we were wrong he had never even
joined Al-Qaeda he was a bad guy he was
certainly helping Al-Qaeda he had been
the founder of al-qaeda's two training
camps in southern Afghanistan he had
been the founder of al-qaeda's uh Safe
House in pesha Pakistan called the house
of Martyrs he was something of a
logistician for Al-Qaeda but he had a
cousin with the same name a first cousin
and so at the CIA we didn't know that it
was two different people and so we're
getting this information Abu zua did
this Abu Zeda did that Abu Zeda is
planning this attack abua is planning
that attack he looked like a terrorist
Superman and it wasn't until after we
captured him that we realized that there
were two Abu zubedas
ah okay that's interesting I all always
uh mess up with Arabic names because
they all sound the same or very similar
so I totally understand so when you guys
kidnapped him this was a raid with
people okay because you didn't want to
kill him you wanted him alive is there
anything specific that you remember
that that that you keep in your mind
that does stroke you back then about
this
rid oh yeah the one thing that is has
always been at the very front of my mind
we had a large team we had four or five
dozen people between CIA FBI Pakistani
isi and Pakistani police we had maybe 50
60 people and I could not have been any
more
clear in my instructions that we must
take him
alive and of course as soon as we find
him a Pakistani policeman opens fire
with an
AK-47 and shoots him in the thigh the
groin and the stomach
and killed him later on in the evening
the Doctor Who was doing emergency
surgery came out to tell me that he had
never seen wounds that were so severe
where the patient lived he said I think
you need to be prepared that he's not
going to he's not going to live through
this surgery and mirac ously he did he
lived through the surgery but it was it
was
close well I've spoken to a lot of
people who have been to Afghanistan and
I asked them how was collaboration with
the local forces and most of them said
that it was a mess because of corruption
because they don't get along with each
other and something like that all these
kind of stories so let me ask you the
other side of the coin of the question I
was collaboration with the
Pakistani well that's actually a very
good question and it's not an easy
question to answer on counterterrorism
it couldn't have been better these guys
were prepared to lay down their lives
for us and interestingly they were the
only ones who never wore bulletproof
vests they were
Fearless but it was my experience that
there were two Pakistani Isis there was
the counterterrorism division where they
were all educated in the UK K they they
had graduated from Sandhurst they spoke
beautiful English uh they went to
Disneyland and Disney World and they
loved American movies and that was just
great but then on the other
side were the guys with the long
beards the guys who would look at you
with dirty looks when you were at their
headquarters these were the guys who
created the Taliban in the 1990s these
were the guys who were collaborating
with the Kashmir uh terrorist groups or
or the or the um uh fundamentalist
terrorist groups in Northern Pakistan in
the SWAT Valley let's
say these were the ones that would just
as soon see you dead as they would to
flick a fly off of their
shoulder so even though they were all
members of
isi we had to be very careful with who
we were dealing uh the counterterrorism
guys were great now you said something
that's also very important and that's
corruption I had never seen this kind of
corruption in my life there's an old
saying at the CIA it's a joke but it's
true you can't buy an Afghan warlord but
you can certainly rent
one and the truth was the same in
Pakistan
everybody was for
rent very
similar well as you said as you
mentioned at the very beginning you said
in an interview to ABC that zubida had
been waterboarded several times so first
off to assess the the argument is
waterboarding normal
procedure it wasn't until 2002 you know
this is something that's actually very
important for me in
1946 we executed Japanese soldiers who
had waterboarded American prisoners of
war in the second world war that was a
death penalty offense to waterboard
somebody in January of 1968 The
Washington Post ran a front page
photograph of an American Soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner on the day that that picture
was published the Secretary of Defense
Robert mcamera ordered an investigation
and the soldier was was arrested he was
tried on a on a torture charge and he
was convicted and sentenced to 20 years
at hard labor at lenworth
Penitentiary the law never
changed we
changed and so my position at the time
was how could torture how could water
boarding be a death penalty offense in
1946 how could waterboarding be worthy
of 20 years in prison in
1968 but in 2002 no problem you want to
waterboard somebody go ahead and
waterboard him and then the CIA and the
military lied
consistently after I outed the water
boarding saying well they had only water
boarded Abu Zeda Khaled shikh Muhammad
and one other prisoner that was not true
that was a lie they waterboarded dozens
of prisoners we still don't know the the
extent of the water boarding and torture
program um you know thank goodness we
have at least an idea thanks to the the
Senate uh torture report
although most people don't understand
that the torture report report was never
actually released the torture report is
about 5,000 pages long what was released
was a very heavily
redacted version of the 500 page
executive summary so will we'll never
really know the extent of the cia's
torture program never we have a general
idea but we'll never really know how bad
it
was well after this interview you've
been charged and eventually sentenced to
30 months for disclosing classified
material disclosing the names of CIA
under cover people and the torture on
Abu vaa of course this closing
classified material is against the law
so so what
happened yeah well there let me take
issue with a couple of different things
that you've said there um it is actually
illegal in the United States to classify
a crime right so if if government is
committing a crime it is illegal to make
that program classified in order to keep
it from the public in my view torture
was clearly illegal we have the federal
torture Act of 194 46 we have the United
Nations convention Against torture which
we wrote by the way and we had the
McCain finstein amendment that that was
reiterated later uh but torture was was
illegal so I was charged with three
counts of Espionage because of uh the
interview that I gave where I outed
water boarding all of those charges were
dropped they were dropped because the
government couldn't prove
that the torture program was legally and
legitimately classified so they dropped
it what they ended up charging me with
was violating the intelligence
identities protection act of 1982 I'm
only the first American that's ever been
charged with that crime I'm the only
American that's ever been charged with
that crime so what happened was a a
journalist um wrote to me and said I'm
writing a book about the Abu Omar
rendition from
Milan uh can you introduce me to any of
these 12 people and he listed 12 people
I said I don't know any of these people
kidnapping was not my thing when I was
at the CIA I was not a part of the
kidnapping team and uh I I can't help
you he sent me a second email can you
introduce me to any of these 12 people
and I said clearly you know this issue
better than I do all I know about Milan
is what I read in the Washington Post I
don't know anything about that operation
and then he
said in your first book on page whatever
it was 165 you mentioned somebody named
I'll say John can you introduce me to
him and I said and this was my crime I
said oh you're talk talking about John
Doe I don't know what ever happened to
him he's probably retired and living
somewhere in the Washington
area but I confirmed the last name now
this reporter never made the name
public so this man was never in any kind
of danger his name is not out there
nobody knows he was with the CIA but
that's what they got me on now the
director of the CIA David Petraeus gave
the name of 10 undercover officers to
his adulterous
girlfriend uh CIA director Leon Panetta
gave the names of the three Navy Seals
who were undercover who killed Osama Bin
Laden to a
journalist and there was a disgruntled
former CIA officer here in Washington
who gave the name of seven CIA
operatives on his website and none of
them were ever charged with a crime but
I exposed the cia's dirty laundry I
accused them in every news Outlet in the
world of committing a crime against
humanity and that's why they came after
me well that was long ago how do you
feel now after so many years do you feel
mistreated no yes I mean yes and no sure
I every anybody would feel mistreated I
went to prison for for two years but I'm
so proud of what I did my children are
proud of me for what I did Senator John
McCain got up on the floor of the Senate
and said that the American people owed
me a debt of gratitude because if I had
never exposed this crime the American
people would never have known what the
CIA was doing in their name and so the
price has been very high but I'm very
happy with my lot in life I'm I'm proud
of what I did and I would do it
again so what we haven't discussed yet
is what Abu zubida actually said to the
investigators but before we get to that
point I would like to understand
something how can we trust someone who's
being tortured because if you torture
somebody that person is going to tell
you whatever you want to hear to make
the T exactly so why am I supposed to
believe what Abu zua
said you are exactly right listen any
any psychiatrist or psychologist in the
world will tell you that torture doesn't
work because the person being tortured
will tell you anything literally
anything they think you want to hear
just to get you to stop torturing them
so before Abu Zeda was tortured when he
was being in uh interviewed by the
FBI you know the FBI is very good at
interrogations and they do it in a way
that's been successful since the
nurmberg trials where they sit across
the table from you and they offer you an
orange or a cigarette or some dates or
some paper to write a letter to your
mother and they establish a report Poe
and they engage you in conversation and
maybe it takes days or weeks or months
but eventually you open up and what Abu
zua told the FBI that was actionable
Intelligence that saved American lives
two things he he explained to us the
al-Qaeda wiring diagram which we had no
understanding of we knew that there was
Osama bin Laden and Iman Asawa had and
then we didn't understand anything else
about the way that Al-Qaeda was
structured and he explained it to us he
explained how there were independent
cells in cities all around the world and
he explained us how decisions were made
we had no idea the other thing that he
told
us was the identity of a terrorist that
we knew only as MTAR MTAR was of course
a
ner and we knew that this person MTAR
was a very bad man who had uh who had
designed a terrorist attack in 1996
called the
bojinka uh operation right so the
bojinka operation was a plan to hijack
as many as a dozen 747s from the airport
in Manila Philippines and to crash them
into buildings all up and down the west
coast of the United States that plot was
foiled by accident when a housekeeper
stumbled on some of the documents and
called the police so MTAR escaped and we
didn't know who he was and Abu zua when
he was asked about MTAR laughed and said
you don't know who MTAR is and we said
no and he said his name is khed shik
Muhammad we had never heard of khed shik
Muhammad before never heard of him
well months later he's in American
custody now as soon as that happened
the CIA took over from the FBI they
began torturing Abu zua he went
completely silent and the
more reticent or reluctant he was to
speak the worse the torture was to the
point where we made him
insane we moved him from Secret prison
to secret Prison from country to Country
finally to to
Guantanamo and we ruined him we ruined
his brain he'll never be released and we
know thanks to a footnote in the Senate
torture report that the CIA says he will
never be released and when he dies at
Guantanamo he's going to be cremated and
his ashes will be thrown into the
sea so the CIA pretty much destroyed
their their source with their own hands
that's exactly what happened
well there's something weird also that
happened in 2005 the
CIA announced that they had destroyed
all the interrogation tapes why did that
happen and again is this normal
procedure it's not normal procedure but
I can tell you exactly why it happened
it happened because it exposed crimes
against humanity so here's here's what
happened the CIA normally does not tape
torture sessions or interrogations but
this torture program was so new that
they thought they could use it as a
teaching tool as a training tool for new
torturers the White House general
counsel at the time Harriet Meers told
the head of the cia's
counterterrorism um Center uh Jose
Rodriguez do not film The Torture and he
filmed it anyway
and then when word got back to the White
House that it had been filmed she saidd
do not destroy the film because it shows
a potential
crime and so what did Jose Rodriguez do
not only did he destroy it but he
ordered um Gina haspel who was his
Deputy to throw the tapes into an
industrial grinder and grind them up so
they could never be
reconstituted now what would happen if
normal person if you or I looked at this
at these tapes and we worked for let's
say the justice department or the
international court of justice or the
international criminal court or the
United Nations or even Amnesty
International this is clearly a crime
against humanity that is being carried
out and and they're and they're filming
it it's like you know the Germans used
to document all of their own uh war
crimes and crimes against humanity
during the second world war well the CIA
was doing exactly the same thing and so
Jose Rodriguez did it so that the people
who had carried out the torture the
people who had designed the torture and
the people who had approved of the
torture could never be
prosecuted that's well there's one other
thing that Abu zuid said that I think
that it's very important he said that
the the Saudi royals had for knowledge
of the attack
because they were actually founding Bin
Laden under the rug yes in an agreement
According to which they will they were
uh letting Bin Laden do whatever he
wanted as far as he didn't do anything
inside the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia is
that
trustworthy I've always believed that
that was true yes yes for for a number
of reasons um when we captured abuaba
that night uh in in March of 2002 we
also captured his
diary um books have been written about
the diary but one of the most
interesting things in the diary was that
he had the names of three Saudi princes
and their cell phone numbers so we
reported this back to headquarters and
we said hey we have a problem here these
are three members of the Saudi royal
family he's in touch with them by cell
phone so we went to the Saudis and we
said
hey we are G to start killing people
even if they are named Al SAA unless you
get your act
together within one
week all three of those Saudi princes
were dead one of them was said to have
died following stomach surgery he was 43
years old one of them was involved in a
onecar crash in the desert and one of
them died of thirst while on a camping
trip in the
desert okay that was
2002 then we learned
later that the Saudi Embassy in
Washington transferred
$50,000 in 2001 from an account
controlled by the wife of the Saudi
ambassador to the United States Prince
bendar bin Sultan Al
saoud to an account controlled in Los
Angeles to an account controlled by one
of the co-conspirator murders of the 911
hijackers why in God's name would the
Saudi ambassador's wife be sending
$50,000 to the 9911 hijackers they've
never answered that question the third
Point immediately after the 911 attacks
the then crowned Prince of Saudi Arabia
Crown Prince Abdullah Al Saud he later
became the king um went to Crawford
Texas to President Bush's Ranch to talk
about 911
counterterrorism all these different
issues he brought an Entourage with him
one of the members of the Entourage was
recognized by the FBI as being a
collaborator with the 9911 hijackers now
he had diplomatic immunity so we
couldn't snatch him but we went to the
Saudis and we said we either want you to
turn this man over to us right now so he
can face charges related to 9/11
or get him out of our country and so he
immediately left for Saudi Arabia and
the Saudis have never allowed us to
interview him in Saudi
Arabia right and
um the fourth thing is after 911 we were
able to trace millions and millions of
dollars
transferred from the Saudi royal family
or from the Saudi government through
Saudi NOS to Al-Qaeda and more than a
dozen other terrorist groups so that's a
long way of answering your question and
saying the Saudi government was involved
in 911 the Saudi royal family was
involved in 911 and none of them have
ever paid a
price well you're the first person who
has been to Pakistan I talk to and
there's a piece of the whole story that
I cannot really understand because
according to Abu zua there was also a
high rank Air Force officer a Pakistani
officer by the name of mushaf alir I
have to read it because I didn't recall
it by who was part of the agreement
between Bin Laden and the Saudis but
what is the role of Pakistan in this
story I cannot put the pieces together
yeah I don't know if that allegation is
true but I've heard it for the last 20
years 22 years um it rings true to me
it sounds true and it comes back to that
idea that there was this wall down the
middle of the Pakistani intelligence
service so on the one hand you have
these
wonderful these wonderful
counterterrorism
people uh who were all educated at uh at
Sandhurst and then on the other side you
have these these criminals whose jobs
are to to fund and to arm and to train
terrorist groups including Al-Qaeda and
let me add another thing one thing that
many people don't understand is that
there is a very deep love between
Pakistan and Saudi Arabia to the point
where the city where we captured Abu zua
fisel Abad was named after king fisel of
Saudi Arabia
because he had given so much money to
Pakistan to develop it so pakistanis
have this deep love of Saudi Arabia and
the Saudis are very generous but they're
generous many times in the wrong areas
for example instead of building schools
they build
mosques instead of building hospitals
they send plan loads of
qurans and instead of building water
treatment plants or power plants they
send money for weapons and ammunition
and training in in various camps
so this is a problem really for the
United States where we've allowed
ourselves to believe over these many
many years that the Saudis are our
friends and they're not our friends
they're our
enemies and it was always my view that
we should treat them as
enemies well let me get to the main
point here that is why did the Saudis do
something that weird or that evil I
think that we have multiple options here
because it can either be corruption like
Al-Qaeda infiltrated the um Saudi
government or we can have like a sort of
mixture in which somehow the Saudi
royals had to let the terrorists do
something to Plate themselves to to
Plate them and prevent a revolt against
the government of Saudi Arabia itself or
we have another option I've heard uh
from uh uh former FBI special agent by
the name of mar rosini you probably know
him because he's very famous who
believes that maybe the Saudis were
actually trying to recruit the 91 I
jackers as sources therefore they didn't
mean any evil but they were trying to do
their job and probably the the guys that
were tusked to with this were not too
smart and they underrated the threat
what you think I think all of those
scenarios are true I think they all play
a role you know my my first overseas
tour with the CIA was in Saudi Arabia
and I maintained relationships with
several Saudi diplomats one of them told
me later on in the late 90s that one of
the reasons why he was so strongly
anti-democracy for Saudi Arabia he said
democracy was the last thing that they
wanted in Saudi Arabia because if they
had an election in Saudi Arabia Osama
Bin Laden would be elected
president so part of the problem wasn't
necessarily that the senior most members
of the Saudi royal family loved
Al-Qaeda or Osama Bin Laden I think that
they were
afraid that the average Saudi loved
Al-Qaeda and Osama Bin Laden and so they
had to try to walk this fine line where
they can steal the country's wealth and
drink wine and smoke marijuana and have
sex with women and go to you know London
and Paris and Monte Carlo and and Los
Angeles Beverly Hills and live The Good
Life life while appearing to be Pious
Muslims to their people and so I think
it was this combination of things that
that many members of the Saudi
population are
fundamentalist true
believers they hated the United States
or they hate what the United States
stand stands for or at least they did in
2001 and they were perfectly happy when
911 took place I think that at the
working level in the government that was
that was for the most part the case as
well where they were perfectly happy
that the US was humbled on 911 but you
know at the same time I remember telling
a Saudi a friend of mine right after 911
it was like the day after two days after
I said my god do they realize what
they've done do they realize this is
going to result in the deaths of
millions of people they have no
understanding of what they've done and I
said something to abua too
when he was laying in in the bed I said
he he told me that that he didn't want
to attack the United States on 911 he
wanted to attack Israel but that he was
outvoted and I said listen you're not
the victim here there were 50,000 people
in those Towers like what did you think
was going to happen did you think we
wouldn't try to hunt you down like an
animal did you think we wouldn't try to
find Bin Laden and kill him and bring
him to justice for this you live in a
dream world I said we're not going to
stop until you're all either dead or in
prison you seriously underestimated us
on this and in the end that's exactly
what
happened absolutely that's what Happ but
apart from what Abu zua said that we
discussed that the evidence is
overwhelming because we have a dry run
funded by the the Saudi Embassy in
Washington we have many things going on
for instance we have a team of Saudi
agents in California uh helping out the
aers and in a few months I'll be going
to La and I want to go see that
restaurant where Omar albumi met the two
terrorists so how come the US government
is so unwillingly to investigate what
happened and blame the Saudis that's
beyond me you know that's really the
most important question um the evidence
against Omar Alay and the people that he
was working with is overwhelming it's
overwhelming now he has pretended to be
stupid over the years he can't remember
anything he he he met those hijackers by
accident they were just happened to be
in the same restaurant it's all
nonsense but I think that the US
government well this is going to sound
horrible but I think that the US
government has
decided that it is more important
for us to continue selling Saudi Arabia
weapons and Weapons Systems and
airplanes and for the Saudis to sell us
oil than it is to further damage the
relationship by getting into something
that happened 22 years
ago that's awful but I I think that's
real
politic yeah that's criminal it is but I
agree with you well John many thanks for
your time I think that we discussed the
whole Topic in a very great detail and I
think that you gave us a very unique
angle thank you the pleasure was mine
the Pakistani angle was never covered at
least on my YouTube channel and blog
therefore many thanks for your time and
uh and thanks for your your explanations
today thanks very much for having me it
was a pleasure thanks everybody else for
watching this and see you all next time
bye-bye